this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
Robert blumen today I have with me Dan
Lorraine Dan is the founder and CEO of
chain guard a startup in the software
supply chain security area
prior to founding chain guard Dan was a
software engineer at Google discuss and
Microsoft
Dan welcome to software engineering
radio
thanks for having me
today Dan and I will be discussing
attacks on the software supply chain
we have some other content in this area
number 498 on CD 338 on Jenkins
and several others on CD that you can
see in the show notes
this episode will be all gloom and doom
but don't despair we will publish
another one later this year about
securing the software supply chain
there's so much here to talk about I
wanted to do an entire episode on
attacks
Dan before we get started is there
anything else you'd like listeners to
know about your background that I didn't
cover no that was a pretty good summary
okay
we have covered this before but let's do
A Brief Review when we're talking about
software supply chain what are the main
pieces
yeah so software supply chain is very
similar to a physical one it is all the
other companies people individuals
communities responsible for taking all
of the dependencies and other systems
that you use to build your software
getting those to you keeping them up to
date keeping them secure
and letting you use them in the course
of your development of your software and
then the downstream side of that as well
we're all in this massive software
supply chain together and nobody is
building code on an island nobody's
Building Code by themselves so most
people working on software somewhere in
the middle of that chain so all of your
consumers all those people taking and
using your software in their day-to-day
life that's how I think of the software
supply chain
if I understand then there are parts
that you run like perhaps a build server
there are dependencies that you pull in
then if you publish software or an API
you become part of the supply chain for
other people did I get that right yep
that's a great summary what is the
attack surface of the supply chain
it is massive right so it's all those
groups all those systems all those
companies all those build servers those
organizations involved in getting you
your code that you use getting you your
dependencies and your libraries and your
services
any one of them can be attacked so the
attack surface is absolutely massive
as I've been reading about this it seems
that certain things tend to get
mentioned a lot
one of them being Jenkins and another
one being npm
am I making somewhat of a biased or
disproportionate reading
the literature or are those really the
points that people are attacking the
most no I think you see that in the news
the most because they're the most
widespread and most ubiquitous systems
there are different spots in the
software life cycle and the software
supply chain completely but they're both
incredibly common and you'll find them
in pretty much any organization
developing software out there today
Jenkins is an automation server that is
commonly used for CI CD tasks so you
click a button it checks out your code
runs tests spills it publishes it that
kind of thing npm is a package manager
for JavaScript and it's commonly used
for both node.js and front-end
JavaScript that people do on websites so
even if you have as a company you're
doing Java or go or some other type of
backend you almost always have some
front-end website somewhere so you've
got JavaScript even if you don't use
that as your back-end language
so that's why npm is one of the most
widely used and most common open source
package managers so because of that I
think that's why we see these two in
most of the headlines
I found a report from Sona type called
state of the software supply chain
according to this report software supply
chain attacks have increased 650 percent
and are having a severe impact on
business operations
some attacks are poor delay have caused
billions of dollars of damage why have
attackers turned their attention to the
supply chain in recent years
yeah I think there's there's no clear
commonly accepted answer here I have my
pet Theory and some of my folks have
shared it but these aren't new right
sonotype is picking up these Trends and
the trends are new but software supply
chain attacks aren't very new they go
all the way back to the early 80s
actually the first one that I found was
from Ken Thompson's famous paper
Reflections on trusting trust which we
can talk about more later if you want
but we've known about these for you know
going on 40 years
but what we are seeing is attackers
actually targeting them
the best answer I've heard for why now
is a combination of a few factors but
the biggest one is that we finally just
gotten good enough at locking down and
applying basic security hygiene
everywhere else
attackers are lazy on purpose they take
the easiest way in when they want to
Target an organization
supply chain attacks haven't gotten much
easier they've gotten a little bit
easier just in with the rise of Open
Source and the more interconnected web
of services that we're using today but
not a market be easier but they've
become much easier in comparison to all
of the other methods we're finally using
SSL everywhere across the internet if
you look back five or ten years we
weren't quite at that level of ubiquity
MFA is finally still taking off even
though it's a bit slow and somewhat
controversial in some circles strong
password hygiene all of these things
used to be much easier ways to attack
with basic fishing campaigns but as
we've gotten good enough at preventing
these other methods of intrusion the
supply chain becomes more attractive
relatively
is it possible to generalize what are
the intentions of the attackers or is
supply chain simply a mode of attack in
the usual reasons may not have changed
yeah I don't think there's the only
thing new about the motivations here
we're seeing all the same Usual Suspects
performing supply chain attacks nation
states cryptocurrency mining ransomware
all of the above
how are supply chain attacks detected
the interesting part about supply chain
attacks is that you know there's no one
type of attack it's a whole bunch of
problems like we talked about it's a
whole bunch of different attack points
because the attack surface is so large
so all the attacks look very different
if you look back just over the last
couple of years the two probably most
famous examples they got the most
headlines were the attack on solar winds
that company back at the end of 2020 in
which their build system is compromised
the second one was obviously log for
Shell or log4j and if at the end of the
following year and these two were you
know they're both categorized as supply
chain attacks people keep saying we need
to improve supply chain security to
prevent issues like these but when you
actually zoom in they're completely
different you know it's not even really
fair to categorize log for Shell as an
attack it was just a bug that was left
sitting around in a widely used code
base for a decade that nobody knew was
there when it was found out then
attackers tried to exploit it the bug
itself wasn't any kind of attack
so yeah I don't think there's an easy
answer for fixing these or detecting
them they're all very different so the
basic patterns of intrusion detection
are things that you would use to detect
something like solarwinds the attack
they faced I'm worth long for Shell it's
about asset inventory static code
analysis s-bombs understanding what code
you're running so you can apply upgrades
faster so they're all very different
in reading about this area many of these
attacks were discovered in some cases
years after the Intruder had penetrated
the network
do you think that's characteristic of
supply chain attacks or that could
equally well be said of all the other
attacks that exist on Networks I think
it depends I think you know a lot of the
attacks that we've we've seen in Cotton
detected like the solarwinds one for
example it wasn't detected until after
the exploit was triggered this was kind
of a piece of malware that was smart
enough to sit around and wait for a
while before doing anything so that made
it hard to detect until it actually
started misbehaving
you know it hadn't had that timer built
in it would have been detected a lot
quicker attacks like jumping back to not
really an attack so quote unquote like
the log for Shell example that bug was
present for a decade and then all of a
sudden once it was found researchers
went and found a whole bunch of similar
ones nearby which caused the fixed
rollouts to be a little bit slower so
it's possible somebody knew about the
exploit earlier and just didn't use it
or didn't hide it or didn't share it so
it remained hidden so yeah I don't think
there's anything remarkably different
about supply chain attacks in general
but there are certain ones they can lurk
around for for a lot longer
you mentioned solarwinds log for Shell I
do want to come back in a bit talk about
some of the more well-known attacks I
want to talk briefly about some of the
techniques that are used as you point
out supply chain is not uh technique
it's a part of the system that can be
attacked many different ways I have a
list here of about 10 or 12 but maybe
you could start with your list what are
some of the top techniques or attack
vectors that are used to attack the
supply chain yeah the easiest way I like
to frame this is by looking at the steps
in a supply chain because they're all
attacked and they're all attacked pretty
commonly you know you start out if you
you know hear that classic like shift
left philosophy so if we start out left
where left is developers developers get
attacked individual ones they're outside
of your company working on open source
packages or inside of your company
that's a whole other angle known as like
Insider threats
but if developers passwords get
compromised or their laptops get stolen
and they happen to be maintainers of a
large project on say Pi Pi or npm now
malicious code can get uploaded there
and we see stuff like that happen very
commonly and that's why registry is like
Pi Pi from the python software
foundation and npm but yet we're now
rolling out mandatory multi-factor
authentication to help protect against
those threats because we do see them
whether it's fishing or targeted attacks
let's drill down into that a little bit
somebody gets the laptop of a developer
who commits to a well-known python
Repository
now they would be able to commit
something that shouldn't be there into
their repository walk us through the
steps how that results in an attack on
some other part of the ecosystem
sure yeah there's a couple different
ways this can happen if somebody's a
maintainer of a package directly on Pi
Pi for example one of the most common
misconceptions or people don't quite
realize with open source code and most
of these languages is that you don't
consume the code directly from the git
repository or something you can but it's
a lot of extra work and isn't
necessarily encouraged or easy instead
most people consume this intermediate
form called a package so if you're a
python developer you write your code on
GitHub let's say and then you turn that
into an artifact or something you might
you don't really compile it but you
package it up into a weevil or a zip
file or something like that they're
called in Python and then you upload
that to the python package index and
then people download that and so if
you're compromised depending on exactly
what permissions you have you could
either an attacker could either push
code directly to the repository and wait
for that to get packaged up and send
them to Pi Pi or if you have access to
the package index directly they could
just slip something into a package and
upload that depending on how users have
their system set up they pull down that
update right away the very nice time
they build and deploy we see this
commonly used to install crypto miners
or fish for credentials on a developer's
machine
um you know steal Amazon tokens or
something like that in a lot of these
cases you know Attack One developer and
then that's used to laterally move to
attack all the people depending on that
package
once you get this bad package then if
it's trying to steal credentials does it
have a technique to exfiltrate them back
to the attacker yeah this is kind of how
a lot of them end up getting detected
they might use some form of code
obfuscation to hide exactly what's going
on but it would usually look something
like a little script that you know runs
scans the home directory looks your SSH
keys or other secret variables you have
stored there and then send them you know
to an IP address somewhere some people
have gotten a little more clever with it
I think the the famous dependency
confusion attack used DNS requests or
something like that that aren't commonly
flagged by firewalls to actual trait
data that way but as soon as you have a
network connection you can't really
trust that the data stays private just
now you mentioned dependency confusion
that's also on my list explain what that
is yeah that was a really interesting
attack or class of attacks I guess
depending on how you want to
characterize it because it affected
multiple different programming languages
that a researcher found some time last
year thankfully it was a researcher
doing this to report the bugs and close
the loops not really steal data from
companies but now we do see copycats
rolling out trying to steal data using
this technique
and the basic premise here is that a lot
of companies have rightly recognized
that publishing code and using Code
directly from open source and public
repositories does come with some risks
they try to use private repositories or
private mirrors where they vetted things
and they published their own code into
but it turns out a lot of these package
managers had some features built in to
make it really really easy to install
stuff where it would just try all these
different mirrors at the same time to
look for a package until it found one in
the order there kind of surprised some
folks so if you have an internal
registry at your large company where you
publish code it turns out that it
actually checked the public one first
for all of these packages and normally
that's not a problem if you have you
know an internal package name that
nobody's using publicly to store your
own code but if somebody finds out what
those names are and happens to upload
something to Pi Pi or ruby gems or
something like that with the same name
turns out you're going to get their code
instead of yours and as soon as you grab
that that code starts running and it's
basically handing out you know remote
code execution one of the worst types of
vulnerabilities of a tune attacker as
long as they can guess the names of your
packages
and that's not something people normally
protect that closely and you don't
really see names as incredibly sensitive
data sometimes the code is but you know
the name of the package is something
that people copy around all the time and
post in log messages and errors on stack
overflow when they're debugging so it's
not something that's widely considered a
secret
if I understand this then suppose I work
at large company XYZ and we have uh
internal repository and perhaps if we're
in a typical perimeter Network
the DNS of that repository it's not
public DNS it's private DNS within the
corporate Network and it's called XYZ
python registry and in that register we
have a package it's called XYZ credit
card charge something like that and
according to
what you said the package resolver and
python might look for that name XYZ
credit card charge in a range of
different repositories including public
repositories and it would not
necessarily prefer the private one ahead
of public ones so you can get ahead of
the private one in the line and
hopefully it will pull your code down if
you're the bad guy yeah that was
basically the technique now it sort of
makes sense if you don't think about it
too closely if you're installing you
know 200 packages 198 of them probably
do come from that Open Source One the
public registry so let's try that first
and then fall back the other two times
this wasn't put in intentionally it was
just something that sat around for a
better part of a decade before somebody
noticed that it could be abused in this
manner I've heard of a technique which I
believe is related called typo squatting
can you talk about that
yeah very similar this kind of bleeds
into the social engineering category of
attacks where it's hard to exactly
classify it but the general technique
there is you
find a commonly used package or a
website or tool or something with a name
and then you upload something with a
very similar name whether it's a small
typo or replacing a character with the
Unicode version that looks the same
unless you actually you know look at the
raw bytes or even more social
engineering versions this is something
we faced a lot when I was at Google we'd
upload libraries with the name of
something like Google Cloud Ruby client
somebody else would upload one with like
Google Ruby client or gcp Ruby client or
you know switching around all these
acronyms creativity is endless here
there are an infinite number of ways to
look make something look real in the
naming conventions are all kind of just
made up these get uploaded and then you
kind of have to sit and wait and listen
to where the social engineering part
comes in for somebody to either typo it
or copy paste it or have it show up in a
search engine somewhere to grab your
copy instead of the correct one
if you're the bad guy then you might
post some stack Overflow questions about
that package just try to get it out
there in this search engines and
hopefully somebody else will
see that on stack Overflow and copy
paste that into there exactly okay
another
technique which if you want to use this
as a launch pad to talk about the Ken
Thompson paper was would be injecting
things into the build yeah so this is
kind of what happened in the solarwinds
case but this is really what Ken kind of
pointed out back in the 80s
so it's a really interesting paper and
the title is Reflections on trusting
trust it's very short I think he gave
the talk actually uh during his like
touring award except in speech or
something
yeah you should really read the paper
I'd encourage anybody working with
computers to do it I mean it's got a
funny story too the story is
um he was at Bell Labs at the time you
know in the group that invented you know
most modern programming languages the
Unix operating system all this stuff
that we still use today when he wanted
to prank his co-workers who are all also
incredibly smart folks like him and what
he decided to do was insert a back door
into the compiler they were all using
when any code got built with that
compiler it would insert a little back
door into that code so when you executed
a program you built it would do
something funny like print out the
user's password or something like that
before it ran the rest of the program
that was kind of the little back door
that you stuck in knowing that the
social really smart and you know they'd
assume it was a compiler bug he made the
compiler kind of propagate this so he
went another level here so instead of
just having this you know back during
the source code building a compiler
handling that to folks you know data
immediately then go build a new compiler
to work around it he made it propagate
so the compiler when it was compiling a
normal program would insert this back
door but if it was compiling a new
compiler it would insert the backdoor
Den into that compiler so it continued
to propagate so he did this gave
everyone the compiler how to kind of
hide and sit and wait for a little bit
deleted all the source codes now there's
no more evidence this back door existed
the compiler just kind of had it there
in the byte code and would propagate
backdoors into every program it built oh
he knew the folks were also smart enough
to you know look at the raw assembly and
figure out what was happening and be
able to remove it by patching the
program directly so he went one more
level I mean you know this isn't in the
original paper I swear I saw this
somewhere in one of those box but I
haven't been able to find it again he
also made it so that when you were
compiling the disassembler that people
would use to read the raw machine code
it would insert a backdoor into the
disassembler to hide the back doors in
all of the programs especially folks
stepping through the code in the
disassembler getting to the section
seeing no evidence of any back door
anywhere and then their password's still
getting printed out because on the
compiler the disassembler and all the
programs have kind of been backdoored at
that level this reminds me of things
I've heard about root kits that can
intercept system calls when you try to
list files to see if you have a
malicious file it will intercept the ls
and not show you the file yeah very
similar to something like that where you
know the back door is operating in a
lower level for you to even be possible
to detect he kind of basically showed
that unless you have trust in every
piece of software and Tool and service
that was used to build the software
you're using recursively all the way
back to the first compiler is a
bootstrapped you know the reprogramming
language then it's hard to have any
trust in the programs that we're running
today because everything to be capable
of being backdoored and then hiding
those back doors there have been some
techniques you know to mitigate this
with multiple reproducible builds and
using different compilers and different
outputs and things like that but it's
all very complicated and scary what
about the role of code obfuscation which
this example you're talking about with
Ken Thompson could be considered an
example of code obfuscation are there
others
yeah yeah these are these are used a lot
a lot of kind of security scanners and
static analog tools we're just kind of
read code and look for things that
shouldn't be doing kind of at a cursory
level and thankfully a lot of attackers
are lazy and don't go through the
trouble of hiding stuff too much so you
can see stuff like things getting
uploaded to random IP addresses or
domains in other countries but some
folks do try to obfuscate it and hide it
you know hide these strings that are
commonly searched for and you know base
64 encoding or something like this and
that kind of has a drawback too because
obfuscated code is generally there's
also scanners that are really good at
looking for stuff that's been
intentionally obfuscated so yeah it's
kind of a trade-off either way
you can take it farther though right
these are all kind of automated
obfuscation techniques that leave some
kind of Fingerprints of what they do
there's manual you know ways to do this
as well there are a lot of bug doors I
think is the technique there where if
you could read code and you know see
every bug then you'd be the best
programmer in the world nobody can do
that and it's possible to write code
that leaves a bug in place that you knew
was there that a reviewer or somebody
else might not notice there's a great
competition each year called the
international obfuscated C code
competition I'm not sure if you're
familiar with this in it every year
people are challenged to write C code
that does one task but then does
something else as malicious as or funny
as possible that people can't see upon a
curse or you read how much if you've
ever seen some of these submissions then
uh yeah you'd probably be terrified at
the idea of obfuscated code Sitting In
Plain Sight I have looked at some of
those submissions I did at one point
know how to program in C and looking at
these programs I absolutely could not
tell what any of them did
yeah and the the operating systems that
we all use today or millions of lines of
code of C written these same ways it's a
miracle any of it works
we have talked about a couple of
examples here the Ken Thompson and the
dependency confusion attack which was
launched by a researcher named Alex
Burson he has a great article about that
on medium
let's talk now more about some of the
attacks you mentioned that I said I'd
come back to starting with the log for
Shell sure yeah that was really a worst
case scenario there was these types of
things are just inevitable over time but
yeah this was a vulnerability and a
incredibly commonly used Library
basically used for logging across the
entire Java ecosystem and Java is one of
the most commonly used programming
languages around the world I see around
the world but I think this program in
log for shell and log4j are actually
running on the Mars rover so not even
just across the world a little bit of
hyperbole this is across the solar
system at this point that's how commonly
used this this code was and it was just
a bug it's an imprison where when the
logging Library tried to log a specific
string it could be exploited to enable
remote code execution again that you
know the worst form of vulnerability
because that means it's downloading code
from some untrusted person and running
it in your trusted environment was
present for a long time it was governed
by a researcher it was reported and the
fixes were rolled out as quickly as
possible there was some chaos obviously
involved because then researchers
realized this class of attack was
possible and found a bunch more at the
same time that the maintainers were
trying to fix the first one so it took a
little while to get them all patched but
in the meantime attackers found it
pretty quickly and started trying to
exploit this over the internet and it
was as simple as typing one of these
strings into the password field on a
website or something like that to
trigger an error message that might get
logged
so people were trying this across the
internet basically and achieving great
results over a couple days until
organizations were able to roll out
these fixes one of my questions was
going to be
I would think that the programmers who
wrote the code have control over what
gets logged I'm typically writing log
messages like cannot connect to database
so my question was going to be how does
an attacker get information to appear in
the log the way they would do that is
they're entering fields in forms which
they know are wrong and they are making
a guess which is going to be true in
many cases that the programmer is going
to log either all inputs or incorrect
input
yeah that's basically correct you can do
this in HTTP headers and you know a lot
of servers will log those you could
stick it in your IP address fields and
stuff like that to trigger intentional
errors when developers want to debug
something in production you know they
want as much data as possible so it's
common to log a lot of this stuff
you know in recent years because all the
Privacy constraints and gdpr people have
started scrubbing log messages for pii
but before that it was pretty common
practice to log everything which might
include usernames and sometimes clear
text passwords and stuff like this which
you know we're a whole Boon for
attackers to trying to steal data for
the most part logged entries are not
considered sensitive and people don't
sanitize it to the extent they should
falling this down the chain I enter
the bad string in the password I'm
guessing correctly that the developer
has a statement says log level warning
incorrect password how does that
translate into some bad code being able
to run on the Java virtual machine yeah
so this is some pretty technical details
and Java you know I think this is a case
of kind of in I think the term I saw is
like an intersection vulnerability where
it wasn't really one commit or one thing
that added the bug it was kind of the
intersection of two commits so we're
both fine by themselves but when
operated together it's unintended
behavior and this happens all the time
but yeah the Java Library here supports
kind of on Macros or template expansion
or things like this in log messages to
make it easier to use and that's a great
feature
and then at the same time the jvm and
Java itself was designed to run in all
sorts of environments right some even
include browsers where you can embed a
jvm in a browser and there's a little
feature where it could go load you know
an applet or something over the internet
and run that in your browser Tab and it
turned out that that was kind of just
left on by default in a lot of these
cases that behavior to go dynamically
load some code from a URL and run it and
it turned out that depending on what
template strings you passed into this
logging Library you might be able to
trigger it to go download code and run
it from the internet as it expands these
templates to fill in other variables and
other contexts into the logging message
so that was basically it there were a
couple other things necessary to get
full remote code exploitation like the
process needed to have access to the
internet to be able to make a request to
go download some code and execute it
things like that but at the minimum
people were able to trigger crashes and
other types of bad behavior availability
attacks that even if the process didn't
have internet connection could still
take down the process and Trigger bad
behavior
if I understand this if I'm the bad guy
then I put a string in my malicious
password or my malicious HTTP header and
that string has in it a small computer
program that says something like HTTP
get
www.badguy.com
backdoor it will load that code into the
jvm it would maybe have a dollar sign or
something around it to tell The
Interpreter that it's code
and The Interpreter will then run that
code and do whatever it does is that it
more or less pretty similar yeah
basically people build like a small
programming language into these logging
libraries so you can do stuff like maybe
split a string or uppercase it or
something like that before it got locked
and there's a bunch of built-in
functions like for example uppercase
like a string or you know adding spaces
or something like that or formatting is
HTML you know these kind of things that
you might want to do before logs get
written and one of the features of the
jvm was that you could also load in
other functions rather than just these
built-in ones you could have custom
formatters or custom you know helpers in
your logging library and if you pass in
a URL to that rather than the function
just a like built-in function it would
go fetch a jar from that URL and then
try to execute that function and from
that jar that it just downloaded from
the internet so there's no guarantee
that came from a server you trusted
there is no guarantee you knew anything
about that code and so that's kind of
how this was triggered people would just
put in a URL containing a malicious jar
and then put the URL to that in you know
this logging string
SC radio has an opening for a volunteer
show host to record five episodes per
year to apply please contact the show's
editor Robert blumen
robert.blooman gmail.com
another podcast I listen to is security
Now
it's a common theme of bugs they discuss
that somewhere along the line there is
an interpreter
or compiler involved
in some cases where you wouldn't expect
it I remember one example of a program
that displays images like jpegs or
something like that
was running an interpreter and somebody
used that as an attack Vector has now if
I know that I'm compiling code
we're not going to get away from having
compilers I'm going to put it on Jenkins
and if I know that Jenkins is vulnerable
I'm going to take a lot of steps to
secure it what's disarming about this is
the presence of these compilers and
interpreters in places where you really
don't expect them so your guard is down
and you're not doing all the things you
would do to protect a compiler exactly
yeah that's a great way to put it yeah
there's a long I guess spectrum between
you know full turn complete interpreter
that can do everything and then very
restricted interpreter that can only do
a couple things that we've told it it
can do I mean it's not always clear
exactly where you are a lot of these
compression algorithms right JPEG and
you know some of these other formats
that you brought up are like little
interpreters um the way that they can
press an image is you know instead of
storing every single Pixel and the
values they'll kind of generate this
little program that can spit out you
know the full resulting image and in a
lot of cases that can take up a lot less
space you know a simple example think
through in your head is you know if you
had a thousand by a thousand image and
all the pixels were black you could
either store you know a thousand by a
thousand little bytes saying this pixel
is black or you could just write two
little for Loops or something like that
and say 4i you know in range for J and
range print black and I know that second
one is much much smaller to store and so
that's basically you know one of the
fundamental principles to a lot of these
compression algorithms items and if
they're not implemented perfectly
correct and you don't know that that's
what it's doing you're executing you
know some arbitrary code
and if that triggers a bug then you've
got you know an interpreter running
against untrusted code
I might not be able to do everything but
it might be able to do enough to cause
some havoc
are you aware of any examples of how the
log for J was exploited in the wild
so there was just a recent report that
came out the odni and kind of an
advisory Council US Government doing
kind of a postmortem on the overall
attack luckily they found that nothing
terribly serious happened which is
somewhat surprising in the immediate
wake of the attack there were some fun
kind of examples happening where people
I think somebody who's referring to it
is like a vaccine or something like this
where you know you're running arbitrary
code there were some like Good
Samaritans that are kind of in this gray
area but they were purposefully
triggering this exploit and instead of
doing anything bad they were patching
the exploit so there are a bunch of
people kind of racing against attackers
in those couple days you know spamming
requests everywhere with you know those
malicious usernames to patch servers
that were vulnerable so it was a fun
little example but I think this is one
where we're going to see a long tail
fall out I don't think there's any
chance at all that the entire world has
patched every vulnerable instance to log
for a shell and that there are a bunch
of if you're kind of Shadow I.T or
machines that people forgot about that
are still running and holding up load
bearing systems this x point is so
simple to do that it's just going to sit
there and then every attacker's toolbox
and as they you know try to laterally
move inside organizations they're going
to test everything they can find against
log for shell and I guarantee someone's
going to continue to find these probably
for the next decade It's Not Unusual you
read about an attack where the company
had a system that contained a bug for
which a patch had been available for
quite some time and for whatever reason
they hadn't applied it
yeah yeah this is incredibly common
there's a bunch of problems here that
make this really hard to solve it's not
as simple as you know why didn't you fix
it we told you to Shadow I.T is the one
big term thrown around a lot here
there's a lot of infrastructure inside
organizations that don't show up on
those spreadsheets and asset management
databases so if you patch everything
inside your company it's like the known
unknowns kind of thing the only patch
the things you knew about no CSO is
gonna you know sit in front of Congress
and say that they patched everything
they're going to say they patched
everything they're aware of by
definition you can only patch the things
you know about and then at the same time
there are so many patches and so much
software flying around that people do
have to do triage you can't just patch
everything and apply every patch that
comes in people need to make risk-based
decisions here I use a signal to noise
ratio is so large if you take a very
up-to-date very commonly used container
image today that are used all over cloud
like Docker images or something and you
run all these scanners against it you're
gonna find hundreds of vulnerabilities
some have patches some don't most are
marked as low or medium severity unless
you read every single one to figure out
the exact circumstances that can be
triggered you don't know if you need to
kind of stop what you're doing and Patch
it so for the most part people set
thresholds and monitoring based on
criticality numbers and scores and
basically try to do the best they can
with what they know about
I want to move on to another one of
these attacks that I promise to come
back to solar winds
what was that about sure yeah so the
solarwinds organization it's a company
they make a whole bunch of different
pieces of software one of them was this
kind of network monitoring software
software like that is typically
installed in very sensitive environments
and monitors networks to look for
attacks so it's kind of looking through
lots of packets and seeing lots of
sensitive information fly by as it does
its job what happened is the build
server at solarwind compromised through
some kind of chain of traditional
attacks but an attacker got a footprint
on the actual build server
this was the server where the source
code was uploaded to you know it ran
some compilation step and signed and
sent out the kind of executable at the
end and that's how the code was
delivered to end users the attackers you
know instead of just compromising
solarwinds organization and doing
ransomware stealing their data or
something instead had their little back
door on the server watch for the
compiler to start drop in some extra
source code files wait for the compiler
to finish and then delete them at the
end so not really back during the
compiler itself but passing in some bad
input right before it started so
slightly different from the Ken Thompson
example but pretty similar in effect so
if you looked at fetch the right source
code it ran the build and here's the
thing it got in the end just it also had
this little malicious element inside of
it then that software was uploaded
shipped all your paying customers they
installed it and the code got to do
whatever I wanted at that point this is
one where it waited some kind of random
number of days after installation but
pretty long period of time to avoid any
immediate detection and then it would
start sniffing collecting data and then
uploading it to some endpoints
it was eventually caught because of that
when it actually became active it's not
Network traffic they didn't expect it's
a little hard to detect because you know
this system was installed or updated in
you know weeks or days before not
immediately right if you update a new
version and all of a sudden Network
traffic you don't expect happens
immediately it's pretty easy to pinpoint
what happened but by waiting a little
bit it makes it a little bit harder to
pin down the root cause
the company figured out what happened a
bunch of research figured out exactly
how the attack was carried out tore down
that Billet system did a bunch of work
to improve security there but at that
point a lot of damage has been done to
all of the users
this example illustrates the point you
made at the beginning about how
everybody's output is part of the supply
chain
somebody else's input so although the
original attack
was on the vendor that was used to
inject the back door into the supply
chain further Downstream of their
customers
exactly these attacks kind of they take
a little bit more patience you can't
quite be as targeted in them but they
have much broader ranging consequences
right you can Target one organization
with a traditional attack with a supply
chain in fact you're kind of left to who
applies updates and who that
organization's customers are but instead
of one organization you're getting
dozens hundreds thousands however many
folks use this software
I think I read Alex Burson the
dependency confusion researcher when he
put out some of these packages he didn't
know which Enterprises would be pulling
his package he only figured that out
when he was able to exfiltrate from
within those Enterprises and see where
his code ended up yeah I think he I'm
trying to remember the original block
votes I think there might have been a
few yeah I think it was a mix of
guessing and then also there were some
targeted ones where companies would you
know just put their name to prefix the
package or something like that to
trigger it to go to the internal one so
I think it was a mix of semi-targeted
versus just let's upload stuff and see
who downloads it moving on then another
one of these attacks which came in
through a development tool is known as
code Cub are you familiar with that one
yup so codecov is a product and they
also offer like a free version of it for
open source repositories to do code
coverage analysis so when you run your
tests it attempts to figure out what
percentage of your code the tests
exercised so generally the more the
better and it's very commonly used
across open source you know if you're
running on GitHub or something like that
in the CI systems you can just drop this
plugin in and you get a neat little UI
showing you your code coverage over time
they had an installer for this in CI
systems it was just a bash drift
basically installation instructions were
downloading and run this bash script
from a URL
um it was a similar case where an
attacker kind of pivoted they targeted
codecov found I think the root cause was
found a secret to an S3 bucket or
something like that for codecov use that
to look around what was in the bucket
saw that this install script was in
there realized that whatever's in this
install script is what was getting
downloaded and run by all of these CI
jobs
they just inserted a couple lines to
that script every time it was updated to
grab all of the environment variables
grab whatever was on disk that it could
find in the server and upload it to a
URL then this one undetected for a while
you know they would put it in and take
it back out for a little while the
attacker would change it on again and
off again over time so it wasn't always
present and anybody you know MCI systems
using codecov during this breach had to
evaluate the impact of having all of
their other secrets and data from that
CI job actual trade into some
organization
so this was a supply chain attack that
also attacked other Supply chains I
guess because these are all other tools
that are used some of the examples I
found with the code gov script you know
right before and after the code Cub
script in CI were secrets to sign upload
code to Maven Central for certain open
source projects I mean these are the
types of things that got you know actual
traded during this attack
so it was like one pivot from the
organization to their users and then I'd
be surprised if you know there weren't
other Secrets stolen in this that are
currently being held or had been used
for further attacks down the supply
chain do you know any more about how
that was detected
you said people noticed it was
exfiltrating I believe I can't say for
sure but I believe somebody just after
months and months some user actually
just downloaded the search from the URL
and read it and saw some weird code at
the bottom and filed some bug I'm saying
hey what are these two lines doing and
that triggered a detection another
well-known incident was known as icon
burst are you familiar with with that
one yeah so I believe this was a
compromise package on npm that had some
malicious code inserted inside of it npm
is like I said the the most widespread
and most largest repository by far so
most of the headlines you see about
compromises like this do happen in npm
just because of the sheer numbers but
this type of thing happens in all of the
other package managers and Registries
too
um I don't remember the root cause for
that one exactly how the package was
compromised it could have been somebody
there's a bunch of different patterns we
see like an individual developer gets
compromised we even didn't see people
compromise their own packages over time
these kind of got called ransomware over
the last couple of or not ransomware
protests wear over the last couple of
years we've seen that a few times but
there's tons of different ways it can
happen and depending on how widely used
these packages are the impact varies a
lot sometimes they're caught before
anybody uses them sometimes they're
caught much later
just one more this will be the last
incident it's a little different and it
came in through a chat application this
one is called iron tiger do you have a
background in that one yeah so I think
iron tiger was the group that was
expected for doing this the code name
for the APD or advanced persistent
threat yeah so this was a chat
application I think it was called Mimi
commonly used in China and the chat
applications for all sorts of different
phones and Opera desktop operating
systems and everything and so malware
was inserted into one of the
installers for Mimi at the distribution
server so very similar to the code Cub
example just instead of a development
tool this was the chat application so
it's built uploaded to this server and
somebody had compromised that server so
it wasn't the build server it was the
place that the packages were stored and
downloaded from every time a new version
got uploaded and the attackers grabbed
that added some malware to it and then
put it back in this modified form so
anybody installing it and using that
installer actually grabbed a compromised
version rather than the intended version
I want to wrap up here in reviewing
these different attacks it's hard for me
to see much commonality other than that
in some way they involve the supply
chain but I'm having trouble drawing any
really top 10 Lessons Learned what's
your perspective on that are there any
real takeaways from this or is this more
just about doing all the things that
people already know like patching and
two-factor and protecting credentials
and and everything else yeah I think
there's a lot of like low-hanging fruit
that folks already know kind of the
brush your teeth eat your vegetable and
style advice that people know they
should have been doing but kind of never
really prioritize until now that stuff
you mentioned is good yeah use
two-factor auth to prevent phishing you
know patch your software that kind of
stuff
um the other big you really overlooked
one and I think is you know just general
build system security not to pick on
Jenkins it's just the most commonly used
one but uh you know most organizations
for the last decade have been fine with
people just grabbing a couple old pieces
of Hardware throwing Jenkins on them
sticking them in a closet somewhere and
using that as their official build and
deployment machine you would never run
production that way right you would
never run your production servers on you
know a couple servers that nobody looked
at or patched or even really knew were
there sitting in a closet but for some
reason people have been fine doing that
for the build and deployment systems
those are you know the gateway to
production of everything that goes into
production comes through those systems
so it only makes sense that you should
apply the same type of production
hygiene and security and rules to those
that you do to production and so I think
that's the big shift nothing crazy that
has to happen there like we know what to
do just run your build systems like
production systems and you'll uh be
immune to a lot of these attacks but
people just haven't prioritized that
work one other topic that came up in
software engineering radio 489 on
package management is we got into a
discussion about the recursive nature of
package management where your package
manager pulls in the packages that you
asked for
and then it Cascades down to the
packages that those packages asked for
and so on and so on more or less Forever
Until you've pulled in hundreds or
thousands of packages that if you looked
at the fullest you might not even know
what half of them do or why they're
there
and yet we have to trust all that code
is that an insolvable problem or do we
just have to trust that the internet is
good are there ways to
be a little more confident that we're
not pulling in all kinds of back doors
when we run our package manager
yeah that's a it's a great point and
package manager just kind of moved up in
abstraction over time in the beginning
you see how most C programmers and C
plus plus programs barely have any forms
of package management it's kind of
manual and grabbing files and copying
them into your repository yourself this
makes sharing code hard but it makes you
pretty cognizant of exactly what you're
using because you copied it and put it
there but as you know new languages have
taken off they've started to come with
like a more batteries included package
manager it's things like Python and go
and you know JavaScript and you know you
can't really launch a new programming
language today without a package manager
there have been some other kind of
Shifting Trends too right people aren't
brand new to package managers Linux
distributions have had them in place for
years you know you run apt-get or yum or
something like that and you get packages
and their dependencies but what those
systems really provided was curation
right you couldn't grab any package um
you only had the ones that the
distribution maintainers agreed to
provide and patch and maintain
which was a small set but it was curated
it was maintained they would provide
fixes for it you knew who you were
getting it from whether it was a company
you had a contract with or a trusted
group of maintainers that have worked
together for 10 years and care about
security but when you run pip install or
npm install it's not from anybody on the
internet that signed up for that
repository the command looks the same
but the implications are completely
different
there is no trust anymore so you're
getting all of the convenience but none
of the truster guarantees
than containers and other forms of
higher level infrastructure came which
are like meta package managers and then
grab all of these together and bundle
them and you can do pip installs and npm
installs and appkit installs all in the
same environment and zip that up
another one's uh you know called hellum
is a package manager for containers so
you're getting a bunch of containers and
a bunch of other Helm charts and kind of
the kubernetes world through multiple
layers deep at this point and it kind of
explodes
combinatorically so it's one of those
problems where it's grown gradually over
time there hasn't been one moment when
it kind of got out of control but now
we're looking back at it and there's
tens of thousands of things from random
people on the internet getting run you
know used for a Hello World application
I like the way you framed it like do we
just have to trust that the internet is
good anybody that's spent time on the
internet knows that's not a good
strategy just trusting that everyone is
nice on the internet that's not going to
work forever I think there's a couple
you know things we just have to do we
have to get more aware of what's getting
pulled in a lot of that's effort from
the US government in the executive order
from last year around this is focused on
transparency so software bill of
materials are now a thing you know you
can't just distribute software with tens
of thousands of things inside without
telling anyone or without knowing what's
in there organizations are required to
provide that bill of material so people
can at least see what's inside of it and
decide if they trust it with that I
think he's going to come panic when
people realize exactly how much is in
there people will have to start getting
more rigorous about it you can't grab
thousands of things for a small
application people are going to push
back and you're going to pay more
attention to the trustworthiness of the
code that you're using but it's going to
be gradual Dan what does your company do
sure my company his name is chain guard
we have a bunch of Open Source tools and
products to help developers solve all
these supply chain security problems
easily great jumping off point a lot of
this is really just about awareness and
knowing what is going into your code and
it turns out that there's actually a
great benefit for developers and that's
not something that makes your life
harder it actually makes life easier if
everything is done correctly all the
complicated bookkeeping about
dependencies and which versions what
they're up to date applies to your code
too and if you have a really good
understanding of what's running where
you can get a more productive
development cycle rather than getting in
people's way so that's what we're trying
to solve
Dan where can people find you if they
would like to reach out or follow what
you do sure my company's URL is
chainguard.dev and you can find me on
Twitter at l-o-r-e-n-c underscore Dan
Dan it's been a fascinating discussion
thank you so much for speaking to
software engineering radio yeah thank
you for having me
for software engineering radio this has
been Robert blumen and thank you for
listening
SC radio has an opening for a volunteer
show host to record five episodes per
year to apply please contact the show's
editor Robert blumen
robert.blooman gmail.com
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening